## Ali Haider Green card holder

• Charlotte, NC

(984) 2188 048

malih4110@gmail.com

Website: MuhammadAli4.github.io in www.linkedin.com/in/ali-haider-4b013132/

## **Professional Summary**

Python | Data Science | Deep Learning | Statistics | Analytics | Operations Research | Mathematical & Computational Modeling | Computer Vision | Bayesian modeling

Software Skills - Python, SQL, R, Tableau, TensorFlow, Pytorch, Keras, Git, Azure ML

## Work Experience

1/2024 - present

Senior Data Scientist, Bank of America – Charlotte, NC

Leveraging data science to combat evolving fraud patterns and empower data-driven decisions making.

- Monitor and evaluate fraud models using KPIs.
- Uncover fraud trends with advanced statistics to proactively adjust detection strategies.
- -Contribute to sophisticated detection mechanisms to stay ahead of emerging threats.
- -Communicate complex findings to drive data-driven decision-making.

2/2022 - 1/2024

Data Scientist, Lowes – Charlotte, NC

Market Mix Optimization: Determined the effectiveness of marketing campaigns using advanced statistical models, ensemble methods, and Bayesian statistics. This project resulted in improved ROI by identifying the most impactful marketing channels and optimizing budget allocation. Sales Prediction: Developed models to predict sales at individual Lowe's stores during severe weather events. This model improved decision-making and inventory management, resulting in reduced stockouts and increased customer satisfaction.

4/2020 - 2/2022

Data Scientist, HTN Networks Inc (Cisco Partner) – Irvine, CA

Developed and implemented a reinforcement learning and ensemble machine learning model to identify malicious network traffic. Continuously improved model performance through experimentation and testing. Established robust post-deployment checks, including data drift monitoring, to guarantee ongoing effectiveness.

6/2019 - 8/2019

Data Science intern, Rafay Systems - Sunnyvale, CA

Mathematically modeled the problem as a dynamic programming optimization algorithm to maximize the server utilization for a Silicon Valley Edge Computing Startup.

8/2017 - 1/2018

Graduate Research Assistant- Computational Lab, NC State University - Raleigh, NC

Conducted computational modeling to analyze environmental footprints at different supply chain levels. Employed statistical methods like ANOVA, ARIMA, and descriptive statistics for accurate forecasting of environmental impact trends.

9/2015 - 5/2017

Engineering lab Assistant – Istanbul Sehir University - Istanbul, Turkey

Course: ISE 521 Introduction to Operation Research and Industrial Engineering Topics. Grading and helping students to solve and debug assignments in C++ and Python.

6/2014 – 9/2015

Supply Chain Officer, Lucky Cement Limited - Karachi, Pakistan

Reduce overall procurement lead time by coordination of inventory, logistics and suppliers.

## **Educational Background**

2020 Master's - Operations Research - North Carolina State University, USA

2017 Master's - Industrial & System Engineering - İstanbul Şehir Üniversitesi, Turkey

2013 Bachelors - Industrial and Manufacturing - NED University of Eng. and Tech, Pakistan

**Honors and Awards** 

North Carolina State University PhD Fellowship award, 2017 President and Founder of the Entrepreneur Society NED University, 2013. <a href="https://www.nedentrepreneurshipsociety.com">www.nedentrepreneurshipsociety.com</a>

Projects	
----------	--

1/2021 - 3/2021	Multi-Variat forecast of stock prices using LSTM and Natural Language Processing (NLP)
	Developed an NLP based stock trading program that uses BERT model for tweet sentiments and does multi variate LSTM forecasting to predict the future ups and downs of stock with around 54% accuracy <a href="https://bit.ly/39mBnbw">https://bit.ly/39mBnbw</a>
1/2020 – 5/2020	Computer Vision: Grocery item classifier using Convolutional Neural Network (CNN)
	Built a detection and classifier model based on pretrained VGG-16 model and CNN layers to distinguish 25 grocery store items. TensorFlow and OpenCV was used. The model achieved 85% accuracy on the unseen data. GitHub <a href="https://bit.ly/3rqad9G">https://bit.ly/3rqad9G</a>
6/2020 – 12/2020	Natural Language Processing: A chatbot that is wise.
	Trained the model on 700 quotations from diversified domains (phycology, relationships, spirituality, etc.). The bot will give satisfactory answer to most of your hard questions by matching it with relevant quotations. Try it here <a href="http://www.thebhalol.com/">http://www.thebhalol.com/</a>
7/2020 – 11/2020	A Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) for data augmentation
	Implemented Cycle GANs for data augmentation to double the number of images to be used by a computer vision model. It improved the model performance by 10%.
3/2020 – 6/2020	Intrusion Detection: Identifying malicious internet traffic.
	Identified network intrusion with F1 score of 0.997, using exploratory data analysis, feature engineering, and machine learning. Github link <a href="https://bit.ly/3mmUBD6">https://bit.ly/3mmUBD6</a>
8/2019 – 12/2019	Deep Learning: Prediction of Battery Life for NASA's Small Electric Aircraft
	A research project that aimed at predicting reaming battery life using SVM, Random Forest and deep learning on 4 million entry data from 9 different sensors. GitHub Link <a href="http://rb.gy/jfkhgz">http://rb.gy/jfkhgz</a>
8/2019 – 12/2019	Natural Language Processing: Quora Insincere question classification
	Identify and flag insincere questions using LSTM, CNN and GRU. GitHub <a href="http://rb.gy/tlhia1">http://rb.gy/tlhia1</a>

Master thesis tile "The Assessment and Integration of Material Footprint in National Energy Development Plans". Diss. 2017.

Kucukvar, M., Haider, M.A. and Onat, N.C., 2017. Exploring the material footprints of national electricity production scenarios until 2050: the case for Turkey and UK. Resources, Conservation and Recycling, 125, pp.251-263.

Kucukvar M., Onat, NC, Haider, MA. "Scarce Resource-dependence of the European Electricity Production Scenarios until 2050" The International Symposium on Sustainable Systems and Technology (ISSST), May 16-18, 2016, Phoenix, Arizona, USA

Kucukvar, M., Onat, N.C., Haider, M.A. and Shaikh, M.A., 2017. A global multiregional life cycle sustainability assessment of national energy production scenarios until 2050. In International Conference on Industrial Engineering and Operations Management Bogota.

First author and presenter At SPE International Intelligent Energy Conference, UAE 2013, SPE, the paper titled "Intelligent integrated management for new ventures in high risk developing countries" ISBN 978-1-61399-276-0. An energy sector firm's Supply chain KPI were developed using the Supply Chain Operation Reference Model (SCOR) model

Onat, NC, Haider, MA, Kucukvar M, "Material Dependence of National Electricity Generation Plans: The Case for Turkey and United Kingdom", Journal of Cleaner Production, 2017

Sen B, Kucukvar M., Onat, NC, Haider, MA, "Material Footprint of Alternative Fuel Vehicles: A Multi-Regional Input-Output Life Cycle Assessment", The journal of Energy and Environmental sciences, 2016.

Onat, N.C., Kucukvar, M., Toufani, P. and Haider, M.A., Carbon Footprint Analysis of Electric Taxis in Istanbul. 2017

Design of Supply Chain at Amreli steels limited and the study of the Supply Chain Operation Reference Model (SCOR, 2013-NED University Undergrad final project